Many of us have tumors growing
inside of us right now.
While most people
develop cancer,
slowing its growth can help us
unknowingly live with it
rather than die from it.
Watch the video
to learn more.
"How to Slow Cancer Growth"
One cancer cell
never hurt anyone.
Two cancer cells
But a billion cancer cells?
That's when we start
getting into trouble.
So, we have to slow,
even reverse,
the division and growth
of cancer cells.
We all have cells
that could grow into tumors,
but if we slow them down,
our immune systems
may have a chance
to clean them up
before they hurt us.
Take breast cancer,
for example,
the most common internal cancer
among American women.
Like all cancers,
it starts with a single cell.
This is a photomicrograph
(a photograph
taken under a microscope)
of an actual
breast cancer cell
which then divides
and becomes two cells,
then four, then eight,
and so on.
Every time the cells divide,
the tiny tumor
doubles in size.
It only needs to double
about 30 times,
and we're up to
a billion cancer cells,
which is a tumor
just large enough
to be felt and picked up
by mammography.
Even though a tumor
only has to double 30 times,
it may take anywhere
from about 50 days
to a thousand days
for a cancer cell
to double just once.
So, that means from the time
that first cell mutates,
it takes between a few years
and nearly a century
before it grows to show up
as a little tumor we can see.
The shortest known interval
between exposure to a carcinogen
and the development of cancer
is about 18 months,
which is when
some of the first leukemia cases
started appearing
after Hiroshima.
Cancers need time to grow,
and for most solid tumors,
meaning non-blood tumors,
cancer takes decades to develop.
Check it out:
the ovarian cancer
you get diagnosed with
at the average age of 62
started growing
44 years earlier.
So, you've had cancer
since you were 18 years old,
you just didn't know it.
Some breast cancers
may even start in the womb
before we're even born,
and may depend in part
on what your mom ate.
The process
of cancer development
happens in stages.
The first stage of cancer
is cancer initiation,
the irreversible DNA mutation
that turns that first cell bad.
But then we move to
the promotion stage of cancer,
which is reversible.
If we don't promote
the tumor growth
it can stay hidden forever
or even disappear.
When I was a teen
I ate a lot of processed meat,
bacon, hot dogs,
known human carcinogens,
meaning they cause cancer.
I very well may have mutated
one of the cells in my colon.
It can take 50 years
for colon cancer to show up
after it's been initiated.
Cancer may have been initiated
by a DNA mutation,
but if we don't promote it,
if we keep it dormant,
if we slow it down,
we may be able to even reverse
its growth.
I mean, I don't care
if the cancer shows up
a hundred years from now.
I don't imagine I'll be around
to worry about it.
Take prostate cancer.
More men die
with prostate cancer
than because of it.
According to autopsy studies
in Japan,
there is about as much
hidden prostate cancer there
as we have in the United States.
But their risk of dying
from prostate cancer
was 40 times lower,
until they started
westernizing their diets
and started eating more like us,
with more animal foods,
fewer plants.
Japan has among
the longest life expectancies,
but when Japanese men
finally do die,
many have tiny prostate tumors.
But they die with their cancer,
instead of from their cancer.
By their 60s,
the majority of men,
nearly two-thirds,
have tiny
prostate cancer tumors
whether they know it or not,
and nearly one in three men
in their thirties
is already brewing cancer
in their prostates.
Similarly, if you look
at forensic autopsies
of middle-aged women,
more than a third
were already harboring cancer
in their breast when they were
only in their 40s.
Yet the risk of dying
from breast cancer at that age
is less than one percent.
In fact, your cumulative risk
of ever dying from breast cancer
in your lifetime
is less than four percent.
So, most breast cancers,
just like most prostate cancers,
grow so slowly that
you can live your whole life
not even knowing
you have them.
It's like atherosclerosis.
About half of young Americans
already have
atherosclerotic plaques,
hardening
of their coronary arteries,
by their twenties.
So, what we think of as diet
and lifestyle prevention
for both
of our leading killers,
heart disease and cancer,
may actually be diet
and lifestyle treatment.
At this very moment,
many of us have tumors
growing inside of us;
so, we can't wait until later
to start eating healthier.
We have to start now.
How can we slow down
and even reverse cancer
while it's still microscopic?
Well, for prostate
and breast cancers,
those tissues
tend to be sensitive
to growth-promoting hormones.
Scientists from UCLA placed
women on a plant-based diet
with exercise,
and found that the levels
of all measured growth hormones
in their blood
dropped dramatically
within just two weeks.
What would that do to cancer?
The researchers
drew the women's blood
before and after
those two weeks
and dripped them onto three
types of breast cancer cells
growing in petri dishes.
Here's the before,
cancer growth powering away
at 100 percent;
and here's the after.
After just two weeks of eating
healthfully and walking,
the blood of women
on the plant-based diet
reduced their cancer growth
rates by 12 percent.
And cancer cell death,
apoptosis,
shot up by 24 percent.
After just two weeks
of moving on a plant-based diet,
the blood circulating
throughout their entire bodies
was that much more
inhospitable to cancer.
At this very moment,
many of us have tumors
growing inside of us,
so we can't wait
until we're older
to start eating
and living healthier.
We have to start now...tonight.